<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition on that most excellent prayer in the liturgy of the Church of England called the litany Wherein all or most ot the exceptions that have been made against it, are fully answered.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3888DA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220212</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831634</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831634</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36099</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39077)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36099)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2125:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition on that most excellent prayer in the liturgy of the Church of England called the litany Wherein all or most ot the exceptions that have been made against it, are fully answered.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Brabazon Aylmer, at the Three Pigeons against the Royal Exchange in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 3 and running title reads: An exposition on the litany.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on verso of final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36099:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXPOSITION ON THAT Moſt Excellent Prayer IN THE <hi>LITURGY</hi> OF THE Church of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> CALLED <hi>The LITANY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein <hi>All</hi> or <hi>Moſt</hi> of the <hi>Exceptions</hi> that have been made againſt <hi>It,</hi> are fully anſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1698.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36099:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:36099:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb facs="tcp:36099:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36099:3"/>
            <head>AN EXPOSITION ON THE LITANY.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>LITANY</hi> is a Word of a <hi>Greek</hi> Original, which ſignifies Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Prayer; ſo that <hi>The Litany</hi> is as much as, <hi>The Supplication</hi> or <hi>The Prayer,</hi> deſervedly ſo called by way of <hi>Eminency;</hi> as the <hi>Beſt</hi> of Humane Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. It begins with a moſt <hi>Solemn</hi> and <hi>Devout</hi> Addreſs made to the <hi>Three</hi> ſeveral <hi>Perſons</hi> in the <hi>Holy Trinity</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, and then to <hi>them</hi> All conjoyntly as three <hi>Hypoſtaſes</hi> of <hi>One</hi> and the ſame <hi>God, One</hi> and the ſame <hi>Fountain</hi> of all <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> whence <hi>Miſerable Sinners</hi> muſt hope to obtain Forgiveneſs. But to wave <hi>that</hi> (as being <hi>Forreign</hi> to my preſent Deſign to diſcourſe of that moſt glorious and incomprehenſible <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi>) and conſider the <hi>Subject</hi> Matter of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36099:4"/>the <hi>Prayer</hi> it ſelf; which is ſo <hi>Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive</hi> as to leave out very <hi>little,</hi> and ſo <hi>Pithy</hi> and <hi>Expreſſive</hi> as to have little <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant</hi> or <hi>ſuperfluous.</hi> The Matter is double; <hi>Deprecation</hi> of <hi>Evil,</hi> and <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> for <hi>Good;</hi> both urged with moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and proper <hi>Arguments</hi> as we ſhall ſee.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Deprecation</hi> of <hi>Evil,</hi> whether <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent,</hi> or <hi>imminent;</hi> or probable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide us. And that is either of <hi>Sin</hi> or <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Evil</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> and that is alſo Two-fold, <hi>paſt</hi> or <hi>future. Firſt,</hi> Sin <hi>paſt,</hi> whether committed by our <hi>ſelves</hi> or by <hi>thoſe</hi> that went before us; the <hi>Guilt</hi> whereof may not be expiated or depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated ſufficiently till the <hi>third</hi> and <hi>fourth</hi> Generation according to the <hi>Second</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; and <hi>that</hi> is done in theſe words. <hi>Remember not, Lord, our Offences, nor the Offences of our Fore-fathers, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take thou Vengeance of our Sins: Spare us, good Lord, ſpare thy People— and be not angry with us for ever.</hi> And this <hi>Supplication</hi> is grounded upon this ſtrong Argument; that we are <hi>redeemed by the moſt pretious Blood</hi> of the Son of God. And ſo we do in effect ſay, Let the <hi>Blood</hi> of our Lord Chriſt <hi>ſpeak better
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36099:4"/>things</hi> for us than the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Abel;</hi> let not our <hi>Sins</hi> nor the <hi>Sins</hi> of our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors</hi> cry louder to Heaven for <hi>Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> than the <hi>Sufferings</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> of God for <hi>Forgiveneſs. Redeemed by his moſt pretious Blood;</hi> ſo <hi>pretious,</hi> that it is the Cauſe, for which God is <hi>not angry with us for ever;</hi> and for which we may hope he will not keep his Anger any longer, he will not <hi>Remember our Offences, nor the Offences of our Fore-fathers.</hi> This <hi>Supplication</hi> is not only agreeable to, but in a manner taken out of the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. O remember not againſt us former Iniquities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa</note> — or (as in the Margent) <hi>the Iniquities of them that were before us. Be not Wroth very ſore, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa</note> 
               <hi>neither remember Iniquity for ever: Behold, ſee, we beſeech thee, we are all thy People.</hi> And here upon this occaſion I ſhall take leave once for all to tell the <hi>Reader,</hi> that thoſe Men do not argue with Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that ſay our <hi>Liturgy</hi> is a <hi>Tranſlation</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh Maſs-book;</hi> for neither is <hi>that</hi> true as to the <hi>Whole,</hi> nor the Argument cogent as to the <hi>Parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It is not true as to the <hi>Whole;</hi> for many things are added, as this <hi>Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and others to be mentioned after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; and more omitted, as to give one notorious <hi>Inſtance;</hi> After the Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36099:5"/>of the <hi>three</hi> ſeveral <hi>Perſons</hi> and then the whole <hi>Trinity,</hi> they interſert I know not how many <hi>Ora pro Nobis</hi>'s or Invocations of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> as thus, <hi>Holy Mary, Holy Mother of God, Holy Virgin of Virgins, Holy Michael, Holy Gabriel, Holy Raphael,</hi> pray for us. <hi>All ye Holy Angels and Arch-angels of God, All ye holy Orders of bleſſed Spirits, All ye holy Patriarchs and Prophets,</hi> pray for us. <hi>All ye holy Apoſtles and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, All ye holy Diſciples of our Lord and Innocents, All ye holy Martyrs, Holy Confeſſors, Holy Monks and Eremites, Holy Virgins,</hi> pray ye for us. Theſe are <hi>general;</hi> but beſides, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> are all particularly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd, and other <hi>He</hi> and <hi>She</hi>-Saints, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſeveral of their Companions, whereof <hi>S. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula</hi> had no leſs than <hi>eleven</hi> thouſand.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. Chap. 15, &amp;c.</note> Surely, <hi>They</hi> prayed neither <hi>with the Spirit,</hi> nor <hi>with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> that by ſuch <hi>Invocations</hi> derogated from our <hi>Lord</hi>'s Interceſſion, and attributed <hi>Omniſcience</hi> and <hi>Omnipreſence</hi> (incommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicable Attributes of God) to ſo many <hi>Saints,</hi> whereof <hi>ſeveral</hi> were far from being <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>ſome</hi> ſo far as never to have had a <hi>Being,</hi> but in their <hi>Legends</hi> and <hi>Bead-Rolls.</hi> God be thanked, that gave our firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> ſo much <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> and ſo much of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36099:5"/>as with a <hi>Refiner's</hi> Fire they <hi>ſevered</hi> the <hi>Gold</hi> from the <hi>Droſs;</hi> and gave unto <hi>God</hi> the things that were <hi>God's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> For thoſe things that are <hi>tranſlated</hi> out of the <hi>Maſs-book,</hi> they are none of them <hi>Popiſh,</hi> nor ever the more ſo for being uſed by them that own'd the <hi>Pope's</hi> Authority. 'Tis a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſay, Where was your <hi>Litany</hi> or <hi>Liturgy</hi> before that <hi>Tranſlation?</hi> It is juſt like that of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> Where was your <hi>Religion</hi> before <hi>Luther?</hi> The ſame Anſwer will therefore ſerve both; Our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liturgy</hi> were before <hi>Luther,</hi> but much corrupted and polluted and diſguiſed at and before <hi>his</hi> time; but a <hi>thouſand</hi> or <hi>twelve</hi> hundred Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>that,</hi> they were what they are now reſtored to, <hi>Pure</hi> and <hi>Genuine;</hi> without <hi>Mask</hi> or <hi>Paint,</hi> without <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</hi> It is as much as if one ſhould ask a <hi>Noble-man,</hi> whoſe <hi>Anceſtors</hi> for ſeveral Generations had been ſo great <hi>Spend thrifts</hi> as to bring a vaſt <hi>Patrimony</hi> to a ſmall <hi>Annuity,</hi> and left him to ſeek his <hi>Fortune,</hi> and he through his own Vertue and <hi>Prince's</hi> Favour ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd to the Place and Honour due to his <hi>Ancientry:</hi> If an Upſtart <hi>Malepert Gentleman</hi> ſhould ask him, Where was his <hi>Nobility</hi> before ſuch a late <hi>King;</hi> He
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36099:6"/>would anſwer, My <hi>Nobility</hi> was before the <hi>Conquerour, &amp;c.</hi> Before <hi>Luther,</hi> before that <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> they ask; We anſwer, before <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> before <hi>Pope Eleutherius,</hi> in the <hi>Councils</hi> and <hi>Writings</hi> of the <hi>Fathers</hi> for the firſt <hi>five hundred</hi> Years, in the Scriptures of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Teſtament; what we have in our <hi>Liturgy, Articles,</hi> and <hi>Homilies,</hi> was fetch'd from thence, and to them we make our <hi>Appeals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having interpoſed thus much, I now go on; our <hi>Church</hi> teacheth us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precate</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sin <hi>future,</hi> as the great <hi>Evil</hi> and <hi>Miſchief,</hi> together with the Cauſes and Effects thereof; <hi>Firſt,</hi> the <hi>Cauſes, the Craſts and Aſſaults of the Devil;</hi>— for the <hi>Devil</hi> is both a ſly <hi>Serpent</hi> and a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Lyon;</hi> where <hi>Force</hi> will not do, there he uſeth <hi>Fraud,</hi> and when his <hi>Fraud</hi> is detected, he flies to main <hi>Force;</hi> but he is dangerous both ways, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be fear'd, ſhunn'd, and depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the <hi>Effects;</hi> the firſt and immediate Effect is the <hi>Wrath</hi> of God; the laſt and utmoſt is <hi>everlaſting Damnation.</hi> And ſurely we ought ever to fear <hi>that</hi> that is Everlaſting, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think our ſelves too ſecure from the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36099:6"/>Danger of it, nor paſt Praying againſt it; the greateſt Degree of Aſſurance at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable in this World, can riſe no higher than that of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.12, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Let him that ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall.</hi> But here I would fain know with what <hi>Spirit</hi> or with what <hi>Senſe they</hi> Pray this Prayer— <hi>From the Aſſaults of the Devil, thy Wrath, and everlaſting Damnation, Good Lord, deliver us,</hi> that can ſo often, and ſo boldly ſay, <hi>the Devil take,</hi> and <hi>God damn</hi> either themſelves or others. I ſay, with what <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>Senſe</hi> do they Pray, that contradict themſelves ſo deſperately; and make the <hi>Throne</hi> of Grace a <hi>Refuge</hi> of Lies? When the <hi>Diſciples</hi> would have fetch'd Fire from Heaven, our Lord tells them, <hi>Ye know not what manner of Spirit ye are of;</hi> of what manner of <hi>Spirit, think ye,</hi> then are they that would fetch Fire from Hell; and ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flectere ſinequeo Superos Acheront a movebo;</hi> call both <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> to be <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioners</hi> of their Wrath? The next <hi>Supplication,</hi> is to be delivered from thoſe <hi>Spiritual</hi> Wickedneſſes, thoſe Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſes of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which have leſs of <hi>Infamy</hi> but more of <hi>Malice</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them. <hi>viz. From all Blindneſs of Heart, from Pride, Vain-glory and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:36099:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:36099:7"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:36099:8"/>from Envy, Hatred, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs:</hi> Wherein we pray God to deliver us from not meerly the outward <hi>Aſſaults,</hi> but the inward <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Devil.</hi> For theſe are the very <hi>things</hi> that conſtitute the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of a <hi>Devil,</hi> and the main <hi>things</hi> that he endeavours to plant and propagate in us, as being his very <hi>Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Image.</hi> We pray not againſt <hi>Blindneſs</hi> of <hi>Eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 4. c. 25.</note> but of <hi>Heart. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> tells us what <hi>Antonius</hi> the <hi>Monk</hi> ſaid to that great <hi>Scholar</hi> and <hi>Writer</hi> I will not ſay, but <hi>Dictator</hi> of <hi>Writings, Didymus</hi> that was blind; <hi>Let not the loſs of your bodily Eyes trouble you; for you are deprived of ſuch Eyes as the Flies and Gnats can ſee with; but rejoyce that you have thoſe Eyes, wherewith the Angels ſee, and by which God himſelf is diſcerned, and his Light comprehended.</hi> So I may ſay on the other hand; Pray not ſo much againſt the loſs of bodily Sight, which is common to us with Worms and Flies, but againſt <hi>Blindneſs of Heart,</hi> which will make us ſee no more than the <hi>Devil,</hi> and with which the <hi>Devil</hi> labours to lead us Captive. So the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us, <hi>the God of this World hath blinded the Minds of them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>leſt the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36099:8"/>God, ſhould ſhine unto them:</hi> and from <hi>ſuch Blindneſs, Good Lord, deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> thing here pray'd againſt is <hi>Pride,</hi> another Ingredient of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh</hi> Nature: <hi>Not a Novice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.6, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>leſt being lifted up with Pride, he ſall into the Condemnation of the Devil.</hi> The <hi>next</hi> is <hi>Vain-glory,</hi> (a <hi>branch,</hi> or outward token of <hi>Pride</hi>) and a-kin to it is <hi>Hypocriſie;</hi> for they both pretend to ſomething more than they are owners of. As the <hi>Devil</hi> told our <hi>Saviour,</hi> when from <hi>an exceeding high Mountain he ſhewed him all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World, and the Glory of them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 4.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>All theſe things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worſhip me.</hi> When (vain-glorious <hi>Diſſembler</hi> as he was) he had not one foot of <hi>Land</hi> to give; and certainly whoever belie and oſtentate themſelves, in pretence of being what they are not, are of their <hi>Father</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> according to what is ſaid in the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 2.9 Chap. 3.9</note> 
               <hi>I know the Blaſphemy of them which ſay they are Jews, and are not, but are the Synagogue of Satan.</hi> Next follows,—<hi>From Envy, Hatred, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs;</hi> for theſe are <hi>three,</hi> and there are other <hi>branches</hi> of that bitter <hi>Root,</hi> which are all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituent of a <hi>Devil,</hi> and make the <hi>Fiend</hi> ſo black as he is. <hi>Let not the Sun go
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36099:9"/>down upon your Wrath, neither give place to the Devil;</hi> When Wrath reſts and ſettles into Malice, then the <hi>Devil</hi> takes place in the Heart, and the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God is <hi>grieved;</hi> as you may ſee in the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> the <hi>fourth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 26, 27, 30, 31 Verſes, compared together; and theſe are all contrary to the <hi>Fruits</hi> of the Spirit mentioned in the <hi>Galatians,</hi> for they <hi>are Love, Joy, Peace, Long ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Meekneſs, Temperance.</hi> I have been thus particular in this <hi>Branch</hi> of the <hi>Litany,</hi> becauſe I have long obſerved theſe two things. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Men in their <hi>Prayers</hi> have commonly paſs'd by theſe <hi>Sins,</hi> when they have long inſiſted upon the Confeſſion and Exaggeration of <hi>other</hi> leſs <hi>Malign. Secondly,</hi> That Men in common Converſation ſeldom expreſs their diſlike againſt <hi>them</hi> as againſt <hi>others,</hi> that are more <hi>Scandalous,</hi> becauſe more <hi>obvious</hi> to the Eyes of the World; which whether it proceed from a ſecret In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulging of thoſe <hi>Sins,</hi> or a groſs Miſtake in thinking <hi>them</hi> more Pardonable than <hi>others,</hi> or becauſe it is more eaſie or uſual to <hi>gild</hi> and <hi>varniſh</hi> over thoſe <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> Luſts with ſpecious Names and Titles of Virtue; as to call <hi>Pride</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity, <hi>Revenge</hi> Senſe of Honour, <hi>Envy</hi> Emulation, and the like, I will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36099:9"/>And upon this Score I the more value our <hi>Litany;</hi> and ſhall only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this farther as to this <hi>Branch</hi> of it, that the <hi>Primer</hi> of <hi>Salisbury</hi> hath not <hi>Pride, Hypocriſie, Envy</hi> mentioned in it. The next <hi>Branch</hi> hath reſpect to the Luſts of the Fleſh;— <hi>From Fornication and all other deadly Sin;</hi>—that is, from all deliberate, willful, preſumptuous Sin; for it is Willfulneſs, Preſumption, Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, that makes Sin <hi>Deadly</hi> or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable without ſpecial Repentance; whereas Sins of Surpriſe and Incogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy, which <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls <hi>Quotidianae incurſionis,</hi> and are ſo frequent, that we can ſcarce know when we commit them, for <hi>thoſe</hi> God is pleaſed to accept of a more general Repentance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wherefore it is a groundleſs Jealouſie, that makes this <hi>Objection</hi> againſt this <hi>Prayer;</hi> that it favours the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Diſtinction between <hi>Venial</hi> and <hi>Mortal</hi> Sins. And let me tell the <hi>Reader</hi> farther, <hi>[from all other deadly Sin]</hi> is not in the foreſaid <hi>Primer;</hi> and upon ſearch it will be found that <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> is a very <hi>Venial</hi> Sin with them, that <hi>coined</hi> this <hi>Diſtinction,</hi> and in a <hi>Prieſt</hi> more pardonable than honeſt and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Wedlock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:36099:10"/>2. Then we come to deprecate the <hi>Evils</hi> of <hi>Suffering</hi> or <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> which are of two ſorts, ſuch as concern our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and ſuch as touch the <hi>Publick. Firſt,</hi> Such as may do <hi>us</hi> a Miſchief in particular, inſtancing in thoſe that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger our <hi>Lives;</hi> as (1.) <hi>Lightning and Tempeſt;</hi> from which there is no flying nor hiding, no arming nor fencing; that which doth often ſet Houſes and Barns on Fire, and ſometimes deſtroys Men in a Moment. (2.) The <hi>Plague</hi> of <hi>Peſtilence;</hi> from which we have great reaſon to beg Deliverance, if we call to mind how that <hi>Becſom</hi> ſwept away near an <hi>hundred thouſand</hi> in our <hi>Capital City</hi> in one <hi>Summer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1665.</note> and many <hi>Thouſands</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in other <hi>Parts</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in <hi>that,</hi> and the <hi>Year</hi> following. (3.) From <hi>Famine;</hi> a Judgment (God be thanked) not heard of in our <hi>Land,</hi> and yet to be feared, if we call to mind the ſeveral <hi>Fàmines</hi> we find threatned and inflicted upon the two Fruitfuleſt <hi>Countries</hi> in the World, the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> and <hi>Egypt.</hi> (4.) From <hi>Battle,</hi> that is, not only from proclaimed <hi>Wars</hi> and open <hi>Hoſtilities,</hi> but from all ſudden <hi>Frayes, Quarrels</hi> and <hi>Duels,</hi> which never end well. (5.) From <hi>Murder,</hi> that is, from <hi>Suffering</hi> as well as <hi>Committing</hi> of it. From all violent <hi>Death,</hi> and eſpecially (6.) that which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36099:10"/>is <hi>Sudden.</hi> From which <hi>laſt,</hi> it is not only <hi>Lawful</hi> (whatever private Fancies have ſuggeſted to the contrary) but very <hi>behoveful</hi> to pray to God to deliver us, as that which may ſnatch us away, before we are prepared either to leave this <hi>World,</hi> or go to a <hi>Better.</hi> The Frequency and Fearfulneſs of <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes</hi> gave the firſt occaſion to this <hi>Prayer</hi> againſt <hi>Sudden Death</hi> (as a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi> Perſon tells us;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Hake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will<hi>'s Apology,</hi> &amp;c. Lib. 2. S. 4</note>) and I queſtion not if <hi>Earth quakes</hi> were as <hi>Frequent</hi> and <hi>Fearful</hi> now, as they were in thoſe days, the <hi>Objectors</hi> would be as ready to Pray the ſame as any other. But though this ſort of <hi>Calamity</hi> be more rare in <hi>this</hi> than in ſome other <hi>Countries,</hi> and leſs Dreadful in <hi>later</hi> than in <hi>former</hi> Ages, (ſo that this <hi>Petition</hi> (at leaſt as to us) may ſeem leſs need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful upon that account) yet how many are the <hi>Caſualties</hi> and <hi>Dangers</hi> we are continually expoſed to, that may put a ſudden <hi>period</hi> to our Lives? Which, to beg the <hi>Divine</hi> Protection to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and delivered from, the <hi>Judicious</hi> Mr. <hi>Falkner</hi> looks upon as the moſt <hi>proper and direct ſenſe of this Petition;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Libert as Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica. <hi>p. 150, 152.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>let that Man alone</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who judgeth</hi> this <hi>unfit, condemn and reject this Petition against Sudden Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:36099:11"/>
            <p>But becauſe this <hi>Petition</hi> (as the ſame <hi>Author</hi> ſaith) <hi>hath been much excepted againſt,</hi> it may not be amiſs to return a more full <hi>Anſwer</hi> to it. Although then we ought not to have ever the worſe Opinion of any, whom God is pleaſed to take away on a <hi>ſudden;</hi> as the <hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>York</hi> in the Time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>An.</hi> 1109.</note> who would not permit <hi>Gerard</hi> their <hi>Arch-Biſhop,</hi> who died <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> to be buried in the <hi>Church,</hi> though he had been a <hi>Benefactor</hi> to it, but in the <hi>Church-porch;</hi> Although Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> pray'd for a <hi>ſudden Death,</hi> and had the <hi>Death</hi> he deſired; wherein perhaps he was ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular; for (as the forecited excellent <hi>Author</hi> (ſaith) <hi>to die as</hi> Joſiah <hi>or</hi> Uzzah <hi>did,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Libertas Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica. <hi>p. 151.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>is not deſirable to the moſt holy and pious Men, who according to the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of</hi> Jacob, David, <hi>and our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelf, by their holy Inſtructions at the time of their Death, may become uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the bettering of the Lives of them who ſurvive.</hi> Again, Though, ſince we know not the <hi>Date</hi> of our Lives, it ſhould be our conſtant care and endeavour, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we die <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> or <hi>gradually</hi> and <hi>deliberately,</hi> to die <hi>preparedly;</hi> like the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>faithful Servant,</hi> that knowing not when his <hi>Lord</hi> ſhould come, ſtands upon his <hi>Watch,</hi> and is ready at every hour of the <hi>Night;</hi> Though we are not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36099:11"/>ſo much concern'd to pray that our Deaths may be <hi>fore-warn'd,</hi> as that they may be <hi>fore-arm'd;</hi> and therefore pray that we may ſo ſtand upon our <hi>guard,</hi> as not to be <hi>ſurpriſed;</hi> and ſo ſtand to our <hi>Arms,</hi> as not to be <hi>vanquiſh'd;</hi> yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, I queſtion not, but it may become any good Man to pray to be delivered from <hi>ſudden Death.</hi> Our merciful <hi>Lord</hi> in his <hi>Propheſie</hi> of the ſad <hi>Deſolation</hi> that was coming upon the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> whereof he gave many moſt ſignificant <hi>fore-tokens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 24.36.</note> and yet declared, that <hi>of that day and hour no Man</hi> Knew, <hi>no not the Angels in Heaven, but his Father only;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 24.20.</note> in that <hi>Propheſie</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth them, ſaying, <hi>Pray that your flight be not in the Winter, neither on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-day:</hi> In the <hi>Winter,</hi> when they could not eaſily <hi>flie;</hi> and on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> when many through a ſcrupulous <hi>Superſtition</hi> would not <hi>flie;</hi> and doth <hi>therein</hi> adviſe them to pray, that <hi>that</hi> ſad time might not overtake them unawares. For the ſame reaſon Prayer againſt the Surpriſe of a <hi>ſudden Death</hi> is very adviſeable; that ſo Men may be <hi>fore-arm'd</hi> againſt the Stroke, when it doth come; that ſo their <hi>Houſes,</hi> which they are to leave, may be ſet in better <hi>Order,</hi> (for ſome cannot be perſwaded to make their <hi>Wills</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:36099:12"/>till extream Sickneſs; or if made, Men may always have a deſire and <hi>occaſion,</hi> and yet not always an <hi>Opportunity</hi> to <hi>alter</hi> them; and ſo ſomething of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence may be left <hi>unwill'd,</hi> that may create Trouble to <hi>Executors, Heirs, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatees,</hi> &amp;c.) and that <hi>they</hi> may be better prepared for that <hi>Houſe</hi> or State whither they are going; leſt when they are <hi>call'd,</hi> they may be found not doing their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's <hi>Work,</hi> and ſo fall ſhort of their <hi>Wages.</hi> The moſt prepared <hi>Soldier</hi> had rather fight a pitch'd <hi>Battle,</hi> than upon an haſty <hi>Alarm.</hi> The beſt furniſhed <hi>Houſe-keeper</hi> would take it more kindly to have ſome notice of his <hi>Friend's</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before-hand, than to be put upon a <hi>ſudden</hi> Hurry. So the moſt wary <hi>Walker,</hi> the moſt wakeful <hi>Watcher,</hi> would gladly ſome <hi>Harbinger</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> of Terrours, ſome kindly <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> or ſenſible <hi>Declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of Strength would give him warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſettle his outward <hi>Concerns,</hi> make his <hi>Peace</hi> with all the World, and leave <hi>Peace</hi> amongſt his Relations, pay his <hi>Debts</hi> here below, and get a Releaſe of <hi>all</hi> above Seal'd and aſſured to him. I paſs on</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2dly.</hi> To ſuch <hi>Evils</hi> as may affect the <hi>Publick,</hi> and that either <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Church.</hi> The <hi>State</hi> may ſuffer either by <hi>Sedition</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:36099:12"/>or <hi>privy Conſpiracy,</hi>—the <hi>former</hi> diſturbs the Peace and Health of the <hi>Body,</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> aims at the Life of the <hi>Head;</hi> for the Preſervation whereof, we are all bound daily to pray, and againſt all thoſe things that have any Tendency towards their Ruin, be they open or ſecret; more or leſs intended. <hi>Sedition</hi> is one ſtep to <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and <hi>privy Conſpiracy</hi> another. We pray therefore that the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> may be cruſh'd in the <hi>Egg,</hi> the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <hi>Baſtard</hi> ſtifled in the <hi>Cradle,</hi> all Tendencies that way may be ſtopp'd in their firſt Motions. And then for the <hi>Evils,</hi> that may injure the <hi>Church, Falſe Doctrine, Hereſie and Schiſm;</hi> in the <hi>Deprecation</hi> of them our <hi>Church</hi> diſowns all Pretence to <hi>Infallibility;</hi> praying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which may befall <hi>it,</hi> or the pureſt <hi>Church</hi> in the World. And here let me obſerve, that the forementioned <hi>Primer</hi> hath not this <hi>Branch</hi> in it, <hi>viz. From all Sedition, privy Conſpiracy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; from all Falſe Doctrine, Hereſie and Schiſm;</hi> —The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> being a great <hi>Patroneſs</hi> of <hi>Sedition, privy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy and Rebellion;</hi> and ſo high a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender to <hi>Infallibility,</hi> that <hi>Falſe Doctrine, Hereſie and Schiſm</hi> are whatever <hi>ſhe</hi> pleaſe to call ſo. And therefore in <hi>her</hi> Mouth, and the Mouths of all her <hi>Children,</hi> all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36099:13"/>that own the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> yea, all that teach contrary to <hi>Her</hi> are <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks. Hereſie</hi> ſtrikes at the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> at the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> the <hi>former</hi> is like a <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> which taints the <hi>Blood,</hi> and poiſons the <hi>Seat</hi> of <hi>Life;</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> is like a <hi>Wound,</hi> which lets out the <hi>Blood,</hi> and if not well look'd to may turn to a <hi>Gangraena;</hi> and <hi>both</hi> are ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, that we cannot too often pray againſt <hi>them,</hi> and all the Steps and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies thereto, even <hi>that</hi> that is but <hi>Falſe Doctrine</hi> or ſimple Errour; which perſiſted in and purſued to its utmoſt Conſequences, may turn to <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and occaſion <hi>Schiſm:</hi> And, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> againſt the inward Cauſes of <hi>them</hi> and the <hi>other things</hi> that are ſo Miſchievous to the <hi>State, to wit, Hardneſs of Heart, and Contempt of God's Word and Commandment. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy</hi> is a great <hi>Ingredient</hi> of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and <hi>Stubbornneſs</hi> of <hi>Rebellion;</hi> theſe two are <hi>Synonimous</hi> to one another in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.23. and theſe all ſpring from the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God's Word and Commandments,</hi> which are the <hi>Teſt</hi> of Truth, and <hi>Rule</hi> of Obedience. And ſo much for the things pray'd againſt.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:36099:13"/>
            <p>In the two next <hi>Branches</hi> we have thoſe potent <hi>Arguments</hi> wherewith the foregoing <hi>Supplications</hi> are urged: <hi>By the Myſtery of the Holy Incarnation; by thy Holy Nativity and Circumciſion; by thy Baptiſm, Faſting, and Temptation;</hi>— In all which there is no <hi>Swearing</hi> nor <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring,</hi> as ſome <hi>weak</hi> Perſons ſondly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; as if the <hi>Prepoſition, By,</hi> could not be uſed in any other way or Senſe. But what think they of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>I beſeech you therefore, Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>by the Mercies of God;</hi>—that is, as ye hope to partake of or be Saved <hi>by</hi> the Mercies of God. It is a <hi>Form</hi> of vehement <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, Exhortation,</hi> or <hi>Conteſtation.</hi> So again, <hi>We beſeech you, Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>by the Coming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>by our gathering together unto him;</hi> that is, as ye hope for the Coming of our Lord at the laſt Day, and our Meeting him at that time (of which he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the former <hi>Epiſtle</hi>) and ſuch <hi>Forms</hi> are uſual among all <hi>Writers</hi> and <hi>Speakers,</hi> when a thing is earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.<note place="margin">Chap. 4.15, 17.</note> And ſo we may account for all the <hi>Particulars</hi> above-named.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By the Myſtery of the Holy Incarnation, Good Lord deliver us.</hi> As if it had been ſaid, <hi>O Lord,</hi> to what end did'ſt thou
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36099:14"/>contrive that <hi>great Myſtery of Godlineſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>God manifeſted in the Fleſh?</hi> Why did'ſt thou that was't <hi>in the Form of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.6, 7.</note> and thought'ſt <hi>it no Robbery to be equal with God,</hi> take upon thee the <hi>Likeneſs</hi> of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Man? Was it not to <hi>ſave</hi> thy <hi>People from their Sins?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 1.21.</note> From the <hi>Power</hi> as well as the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of Sin? <hi>From the Crafts and Aſſaults of the Devil, from the Wrath of God, and from Everlaſting Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By thy Circumciſion;</hi>— Thou, <hi>O Lord,</hi> that was't <hi>made of a Woman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.4, 5.</note> was't <hi>made under the Law, to redeem us that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, that we might receive the Adoption of Sons;</hi> therefore thou ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thy <hi>firſt</hi> Blood at <hi>thy Circumciſion,</hi> and thy <hi>laſt</hi> upon the <hi>Croſs,</hi> to <hi>redeem us from the Curſe of the Law;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.13. 2 Cor. 5.21.</note> thou was't made <hi>Sin for us,</hi> and <hi>a Curſe for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By thy Baptiſm,</hi>— wherein thou was't ſo Solemnly own'd and proclaim'd to be the <hi>Son of God;</hi> and whereby thou didſt <hi>Sanctifie Water to the Myſtical Waſhing away of Sin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Office of Baptiſm.</note> and making us Children of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By thy Faſting;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Collect. 1ſt Sunday in Lent.</note> —Thou <hi>who for our ſake didſt faſt forty days and forty nights,</hi> to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36099:14"/>deliver us from the <hi>Surfeit</hi> we took by eating the Forbidden <hi>Fruit,</hi> and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelf againſt that great <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> wherein thou overcameſt the <hi>Crafts,</hi> as after in thine <hi>Agony</hi> the <hi>Aſſaults</hi> of the <hi>Devil.</hi>— By that three-fold <hi>Temptation,</hi> which thou underwent'ſt, and wherein thou overcameſt the great <hi>Enemy</hi> of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind at all his three <hi>Weapons,</hi> wherewith he worſted Man at firſt, <hi>the Luſt of the Fleſh, the Luſt of the Eye, and the Pride of Life, Good Lord, deliver us from the Deceits of the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By thine Agony and Bloody Sweat;—O Lord,</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> then ſet upon <hi>thee</hi> like a roaring <hi>Lion,</hi> and all the <hi>Powers</hi> of <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> were let looſe upon <hi>thee,</hi> and <hi>thou</hi> then <hi>offered'ſt up Prayers and Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with ſtrong crying and Tears unto him that was able to ſave</hi> thee <hi>from Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> was't <hi>heard</hi> and delivered from <hi>that</hi> thou feared'ſt, (ſo may we underſtand that place) <hi>Good Lord, deliver us from all our Fears: O Lord,</hi> in that thy ſelf haſt <hi>ſuffered being tempted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.18</note> thou art <hi>able to ſuccour them that are tempted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By thy Croſs and Paſſion;</hi>— that is, by thy <hi>Paſſion</hi> upon the <hi>Croſs;</hi> or, <hi>by thy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36099:15"/>Croſs; that is,</hi> The manner of his Death, he was made a <hi>Curſe for us;</hi> but by his Shedding his <hi>Blood</hi> thereon he took away the <hi>Curſe,</hi> and made full <hi>Expiation</hi> and <hi>Atonement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By thy precious Death and Burial;</hi>— Upon the Shedding of ſo much innocent and precious <hi>Blood, Death</hi> muſt needs follow; and it need not be counted any <hi>Tautology</hi> to add it to <hi>Paſſion,</hi> ſince we have not words enough to expreſs what our <hi>Lord</hi> Suffered. And let not any think it was all one to us, whether our <hi>Lord</hi> was <hi>buried</hi> or no, meerly to <hi>quarrel</hi> with this <hi>Prayer;</hi> for <hi>they</hi> muſt alſo <hi>quarrel</hi> with the <hi>Apoſtle's Creed,</hi> that hath in that ſhort <hi>Sum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> of our <hi>Chriſtian Faith this,</hi> and all the foregoing <hi>Particulars</hi> diſtinctly, <hi>thus, He ſuffered under</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>was crucified, Dead and Buried.</hi> Our Lord's <hi>Burial,</hi> with the choice Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of it, ſtrongly prove the Reality of his <hi>Death and Reſurrection.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> looks upon it as ſo conſiderable a <hi>Paſſage,</hi> as to particulariſe it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat it as part of the <hi>Chriſtian Cabbala</hi> delivered to him at firſt.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>I delivered unto you firſt of all, that which I alſo received, how that Chriſt died for our Sins, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures, and that he was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36099:15"/>buried;</hi> yea, and to reſemble the <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> part of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> thereunto.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.4</note> 
               <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are buried</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with him by Baptiſm into Death.</hi> And again,<note place="margin">Col. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>Buried with him in Baptiſm.</hi> Next follow, after all theſe Inſtances of our <hi>Lord's</hi> Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Humiliation,</hi> thoſe of his <hi>Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> his <hi>glorious Reſurrection and Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Our <hi>Lord,</hi> by his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> hath given the greateſt Evidence and Aſſurance of our <hi>Immortality</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> and that he not only <hi>died</hi> but overcame <hi>Death,</hi> and maſtered him <hi>that had had the power of Death, that is, the Devil;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.14</note> and to ſhew that he was to die no more, he left this <hi>Stage</hi> of Mortality, and made that <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Aſcenſion,</hi> whereof enough cannot be ſaid. And <hi>when he aſcended on high, he led Captivity Captive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4 8.</note> 
               <hi>and gave Gifts to Men,</hi> by his <hi>Miſſion</hi> of <hi>the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> which was the laſt <hi>Remarkable</hi> in the <hi>great Myſtery of Godlineſs;</hi> ſignifying the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Means made uſe of for the <hi>Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> and <hi>Application</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> for the Benefit of all <hi>Mankind.</hi> And now pray what <hi>Arguments</hi> more <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>proper,</hi> and <hi>likely</hi> to prevail with our <hi>Lord,</hi> than <hi>theſe</hi> that are fetch'd from all the ſignal <hi>Paſſages</hi> and <hi>Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities</hi> of his wonderful <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking,</hi> wherein he ſo much denied <hi>himſelf,</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36099:16"/>obliged <hi>us;</hi> and for the <hi>effectuating</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and making them <hi>Saving</hi> to us, he now ſits <hi>at the right Hand of God,</hi> for <hi>ever to make Interceſſion for us?</hi> What do we more therein, than Pray to our <hi>Saviour</hi> to Save us by thoſe Means and Methods, which he himſelf hath managed and directed? <hi>Nay,</hi> do not <hi>they</hi> mean the ſame thing in effect, that ſay, <hi>Save us, Lord,</hi> for thy <hi>Name's ſake,</hi> for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt his ſake?</hi> Doubtleſs we all deſire that ſo great Contrivances and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings of Infinite <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> that ſo much Coſt and Pains may become <hi>Effectual</hi> and <hi>Saving</hi> to us, in all thoſe Ends and Purpoſes for which they were intended.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> becauſe there are ſome <hi>Critical</hi> Times, wherein we ſhall ſtand in need of <hi>Salvation</hi> and <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;</hi> if <hi>theſe</hi> are expreſs'd, they will heighten our <hi>Devotion,</hi> and make this <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Prayer</hi> ſtill more <hi>compleat.</hi> There are, I ſay, four <hi>Critical</hi> Times; Firſt, The <hi>Time of our Tribulation;</hi> and this we pray rather to be delivered <hi>in</hi> than <hi>from;</hi> becauſe it is very often the Portion of them <hi>that will live Godly</hi> in this World,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12.</note> to <hi>ſuffer Perſecution,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> tells us. This is a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36099:16"/>
               <hi>Time,</hi> wherein the <hi>Devil</hi> is moſt buſie <hi>with</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> us, and uſeth both his <hi>Crafts</hi> and <hi>Aſſaults;</hi> and therefore we need more ſpecial Aſſiſtance. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Time of our Wealth;</hi>— We do not pray for <hi>Wealth;</hi> but to be delivered from the <hi>Cares,</hi> and <hi>Snares,</hi> and <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> which <hi>it</hi> brings along with it: And in this <hi>Time</hi> the <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh</hi> uſe their <hi>Deceits</hi> againſt us, and ſo often pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, that our <hi>Table</hi> becomes a <hi>Snare</hi> to us, and our <hi>Friends</hi> become <hi>Flatterers;</hi> our <hi>Honey</hi> turns to <hi>Poiſon,</hi> and <hi>fair</hi> Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth us more harm than <hi>foul.</hi> In this time we ſtand leaſt upon our <hi>guard,</hi> and are eaſily <hi>ſurpriſed;</hi> and therefore we pray to God to make us <hi>Watchful,</hi> and to <hi>watch</hi> over us himſelf, and <hi>deliver</hi> us from the Dangers of it. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The <hi>Hour of Death,—in</hi> which and not <hi>from</hi> it we deſire to be <hi>delivered:</hi> For at this <hi>Hour</hi> the <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh</hi> leave us; but then the <hi>Devil</hi> ſets on us a-freſh, and would make us, if he could, deſpair of <hi>Deliverance,</hi> and think our Sins are too <hi>great</hi> and too <hi>many</hi> to be forgiven; he would <hi>fain</hi> make us let go our <hi>hold</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and then he knows we ſhall drop into his Bottomleſs <hi>Pit.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>in the Viſitation of the Sick,</hi> we are taught to pray, <hi>O Lord, Save thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36099:17"/>which putteth his Truſt in thee. Send him Help from thy Holy Place; And evermore mightily defend him. Let the Enemy have no advantage of him; nor the Wicked approach to hurt him. Be unto him, O Lord, a ſtrong Tower from the face of his Enemy.</hi> And afterward, <hi>Defend him from the Danger of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,—Renew in him whatſoever hath been decay'd by the Fraud and Malice of the Devil.</hi> Fourthly,—<hi>In the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> And that is a <hi>Critical</hi> Day indeed, wherein, it may be, the <hi>Devil</hi> may be as ready to accuſe us to <hi>God,</hi> as he did <hi>Job;</hi> but he can then do us no harm; there will then need no <hi>Accuſer</hi> but our own <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and he that ſhall be our <hi>Judge,</hi> who <hi>now</hi> deſires to be our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and that he may prove ſo to the laſt <hi>Day</hi> we Pray, beyond which there will be no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, nor need of any more <hi>Deprecation.</hi> And ſo we have gone over the firſt Part of the <hi>Litany, Deprecation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed to the other Part; which is <hi>Petition</hi> for good things, and this is double, <hi>Interceſſion</hi> for others, and <hi>Prayer</hi> for our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Interceſſion;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, required by the <hi>Apoſtle;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1</note> and inſinuated by the <hi>Plural</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:36099:17"/>Number uſed in our <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> and <hi>here.</hi> As feeling Members of that <hi>Myſtical Body</hi> whereof our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the glorious <hi>Head,</hi> we pray for the <hi>Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church;</hi> called <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal</hi> ever ſince the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> days, and in their <hi>Creed,</hi> becauſe <hi>comprehending</hi> all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the World as well as <hi>Jews,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the World now goes, <hi>Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive.</hi> For our <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid, <hi>Go, teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> &amp;c. and all Nations were taught and baptiſed in the Faith of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Holy Trinity;</hi> called <hi>Holy,</hi> not from intrinſick <hi>Holineſs;</hi> for the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven</hi> is like to a <hi>Field</hi> that hath in it both <hi>Wheat</hi> and <hi>Tares;</hi> like to a <hi>Net,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 13.24.47.</note> which being <hi>caſt into the Sea, gathereth of every kind,</hi> both <hi>good</hi> Fiſh and <hi>bad;</hi> but from a <hi>Relative</hi> and <hi>Faederal</hi> Holineſs, ſuch as was <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and from the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> of a moſt <hi>Holy Faith.</hi> For <hi>this we</hi> pray, that it may be <hi>ruled and governed in the right way;</hi> the forecited <hi>Primer</hi> hath not <hi>in the right way,</hi> for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> thinks it can never be in the <hi>wrong,</hi> never prove <hi>Heretical</hi> or <hi>Apoſtatical:</hi> But we that know the <hi>Church Militant</hi> is made up of <hi>Men,</hi> that are <hi>frail</hi> and <hi>fallible,</hi> and often err in <hi>Judgment,</hi> and oftner in <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> we pray <hi>it</hi> may be kept <hi>in the right way;</hi> and the <hi>good Lord</hi> keep that <hi>Part</hi> of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:36099:18"/>it <hi>in the right way,</hi> that is <hi>in</hi> it, and reſtore <hi>that</hi> that is <hi>out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then we come to our particular <hi>Church,</hi> and pray, <hi>firſt,</hi> for <hi>Him</hi> that is <hi>Supreme Governour</hi> of it, <hi>Supreme Ordinary</hi> or <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour</hi> of it on Earth, and ſo our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt's Vicegerent,</hi> and truly <hi>that</hi> which the <hi>Pope</hi> pretends to be over the whole <hi>Catholick Church.</hi> And (1.) We pray for <hi>Spiritual</hi> good things, that God would be <hi>pleaſed to keep our Gracious King, and ſtrengthen Him in the true Worſhipping of God, and in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs of Life; and rule his Heart in the Faith, Fear and Love of God; and that he may evermore have Affiance in him, and ever ſeek his Honour and Glory.</hi> He that conſiders how prone of old the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> were to <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and how many <hi>Kings</hi> of the Earth at this day Worſhip the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and are governed in <hi>Religious</hi> Matters by the <hi>Imperious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates</hi> of an <hi>Apoſtate Church;</hi> or, to look nearer home, that reflects upon the dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Inſtance</hi> of the late <hi>King's</hi> embracing the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, the miſchievous <hi>Effects</hi> whereof who knows whether ever <hi>theſe Kingdoms</hi> may out-grow? I ſay, He that conſiders all this, will think it was at <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſtill</hi> is very fit to pray for the <hi>keeping
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:36099:18"/>and ſtrengthning our King in the true Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God.</hi> And in what follows, We pray that <hi>He</hi> may own <hi>God</hi> for his <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign,</hi> by making the <hi>Honour and Glory</hi> of <hi>God</hi> his ultimate <hi>end,</hi> and his <hi>Truſt</hi> and <hi>Affiance in God</hi> (and not in Man) the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of all he doth. And then we pray for <hi>Temporal</hi> Bleſſings; <hi>namely,</hi> That God would <hi>be his Defender and Keeper</hi> (<hi>defend</hi> and <hi>keep</hi> him, whom he hath appointed to <hi>defend</hi> and <hi>keep</hi> us) and in order to that, <hi>give him the Victory over all his Enemies;</hi> whether <hi>home-bred</hi> or <hi>forreign.</hi> And then (as is moſt natural) We pray for the whole <hi>Royal Family;</hi> deſiring that <hi>they</hi> may proſper and be multiplied. And ſurely this is far more explicit and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular than that of the ſo often cited <hi>Primer, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Regi noſtro &amp; Principibus noſtris Pacem &amp; veram Concordiam atque Victoriam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare digneris.</hi> After this we pray for <hi>all Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons</hi> (the three <hi>Orders</hi> of Clergy in the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church) that God would <hi>enlighten them with true Knowledge and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of his Word, and that both by their Preaching and Living they may ſet it forth, and ſhew it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</hi> And this is according to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed unto thy ſelf, and to thy Doctrine;</hi> — that <hi>they</hi> may be as <hi>John Baptiſt was,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 5.35.</note> 
               <hi>a burning
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:36099:19"/>and a ſhining Light; teach</hi> as well by their <hi>Examples</hi> as by their <hi>Inſtructions. Then</hi> (what is not in that <hi>Primer</hi>) <hi>that it would pleaſe him to endue the Lords of the Council, and all the Nobility, with Grace, Wiſdom, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; To bleſs and keep the Magiſtrates, giving them Grace to execute Juſtice, and to maintain Truth.</hi> Which in the <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Militant Church</hi> is thus expreſſed;— <hi>Grant unto his whole Council, and to all that are put in Authority under him, that they may truly and indifferently miniſter Juſtice, to the Puniſhment of Wickedneſs and Vice, and to the Maintenance of thy true Religion and Vertue.</hi>—And then follow ſeveral <hi>Prayers</hi> (which are not in that <hi>Primer</hi>) which for <hi>brevity</hi> ſake, and becauſe they are ſo plain and eaſie to be underſtood, I will paſs over, and take more <hi>ſpecial</hi> notice of thoſe that are <hi>Prayers</hi> of <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it would pleaſe</hi> God <hi>to bring into the way of Truth, all ſuch as have erred and are deceived. Humanum eſt errare, humanius condonare.</hi> Though we hope and think we are in the <hi>Right,</hi> and none have yet convinced us to the contrary, yet (as before) we pretend not to be <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible;</hi> and therefore as being liable to <hi>Error</hi> our ſelves, we pray for the <hi>Erroneous,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:36099:19"/>that they may be brought <hi>into the way of Truth.</hi> And then for our <hi>Morals,</hi> we are as prone to Errors of <hi>Life</hi> as <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and therefore pray that they that <hi>ſtand</hi> may be <hi>ſtrengthned,</hi> and others that are wavering and tottering may be <hi>help'd and comforted,</hi> and kept from <hi>falling,</hi> and they that are already <hi>fallen</hi> may be <hi>raiſed up;</hi> and becauſe the <hi>Devil,</hi> that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the <hi>Fall</hi> of our <hi>firſt</hi> Parents, lies like a <hi>Serpent</hi> in our Way, and an <hi>Adder</hi> in our Paths, to <hi>bite</hi> and <hi>trip</hi> up our heels, we Pray that God would <hi>tread him under our feet;</hi> according to the Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives us in thoſe very words, <hi>And the God of Peace ſhall bruiſe Satan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your feet ſhortly.</hi> And the firſt <hi>Goſpel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.20.</note> 
               <hi>—It ſhall bruiſe thy head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15</note> 
               <hi>and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then we come to Pray for <hi>all that are in Danger, Neceſſity, and Tribulation;</hi> and not content with ſo general a <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication,</hi> we reckon up in <hi>eight</hi> or <hi>nine</hi> Particulars thoſe that labour under or are moſt liable to Dangers and Troubles. As, <hi>firſt, All that travel by Land or by Water;</hi> — the Dangers of the <hi>former,</hi> in being <hi>bewildred</hi> and <hi>benighted,</hi> invaded by <hi>Robbers,</hi> and wild <hi>Beaſts,</hi> far from <hi>help</hi> and <hi>home,</hi> who cannot tell? And for the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:36099:20"/>
               <hi>latter, David</hi> tells us as <hi>Emphatically,</hi> as if he had gone ſome <hi>Eaſt-India Voyage;</hi> when he only croſſed <hi>Jordan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.23.</note> 
               <hi>They that go down to the Sea in Ships, that do buſineſs in great Waters:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.24.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe ſee the Works of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.25.</note> 
               <hi>and his Wonders in the Deep. For he commandeth, and raiſeth the ſtormy Wind, which lifteth up the Waves thereof.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.26.</note> 
               <hi>They mount up to the Heaven, they go down again to the Depths, their Soul is melted becauſe of trouble.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.27.</note> 
               <hi>They reel to and fro, and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger like a drunken Man, and are at their wits end.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.28.</note> 
               <hi>Then they cry unto the Lord in their trouble, and he brings them out of their Diſtreſſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.29.</note> 
               <hi>He makes the Storm a Calm, ſo that the Waves thereof are ſtill. Then are they glad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 107.30.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they be quiet; ſo he brings them to their deſired Haven.</hi> Here ſome will interpoſe and ſay, In pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>all that travel by Land or by Sea,</hi> we pray for <hi>Robbers</hi> and <hi>Pyrates, Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traitors,</hi> them that delight in <hi>War,</hi> and whoſe Feet are ſwift to ſhed <hi>Blood.</hi> I anſwer with the ingenious <hi>Falkner, He is properly a Traveller</hi> (and doubtleſs is here meant) <hi>who goes upon his allowable or ordinary Occaſions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Libertas Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtica, <hi>p. 153.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If the meaneſt Man in the Country ſhould hear of an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for ſecuring the ſafe Paſſage of all Travellers, he would never thence conclude, that they intended to provide for the Safety
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:36099:20"/>of Robbers, High-way-men and Traitors, who are the great Diſturbers of Safety.</hi> I add, No Prayer can well be deviſed, but ſome ſuch ſmall <hi>Exception</hi> may be made againſt it; all Men are preſumed to be <hi>Honeſt</hi> and <hi>Loyal,</hi> and ſo we may pray for them; yea, we ought to pray, that they may be <hi>Honeſt.</hi> There is no reaſon that <hi>Honeſt</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> Men ſhould be ſhut out of our Prayers for the ſake of them that are not <hi>ſo.</hi> We may pray for the Safety of a ſinking <hi>Ship,</hi> though there be a <hi>Jonas</hi> in it; as our <hi>Lord</hi> pray'd for his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> though there were a <hi>Judas</hi> among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, All Women labouring of Child,</hi> — and ſo labouring under the Curſe of <hi>Eve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.16</note> when God ſaid, <hi>I will greatly multiply thy Sorrow and thy Conception: It Sorrow thou ſhalt bring forth Children.</hi> And we know the <hi>Scripture</hi> to expreſs a very <hi>great</hi> and <hi>ſudden</hi> Diſtreſs, compares it to the <hi>Pangs</hi> and <hi>Throws</hi> of a Woman in <hi>Travel;</hi> for the <hi>Safe Deliverance</hi> from which, as our <hi>Church</hi> hath appointed a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Thanksgiving after,</hi> ſo here a general <hi>Prayer before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, All Sick Perſons.</hi>— And this includes a vaſt Number; all that labour
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:36099:21"/>with <hi>Chronical</hi> Diſeaſes, as the grinding Pain of the <hi>Stone,</hi> the racking Auguiſh of the <hi>Gout,</hi> and ſuch torturing <hi>Ails</hi> as none can conceive but they that have felt; with <hi>Critical</hi> Diſeaſes, as all <hi>Fevers</hi> and <hi>Peſtilences,</hi> which threaten ſpeedy Death; eſpecially <hi>theſe</hi> laſt, that lock up from the kind and comfortable <hi>Viſits</hi> of Friends and Neighbours; <hi>Theſe</hi> ought eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be remembred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, Young Children.</hi>—How many thouſand Dangers are theſe poor <hi>Lambs</hi> obnoxious to; from within and from without; how hard is it to know their <hi>Ail,</hi> how hard to help them; and when they come to uſe their Feet, how ready are <hi>they</hi> to carry them into the <hi>Fire</hi> and the <hi>Water,</hi> to <hi>trip</hi> at every <hi>Stick</hi> and <hi>Straw;</hi> how ready are they to <hi>play on the hole of the Aſp,</hi> and ſport on the <hi>Brink</hi> of the <hi>Pit;</hi> how near Danger muſt they always be, that are <hi>afraid</hi> of none, and <hi>unable</hi> to help themſelves out of any. There is doubtleſs a <hi>ſpecial</hi> Providence <hi>watcheth</hi> over <hi>young Children,</hi> that ſo <hi>few</hi> miſcarry; and doubtleſs moſt <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> over <hi>them</hi> that are recommended to his Care by the Prayers of the <hi>Church</hi> and their <hi>Parents.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:36099:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,—Shew thy Pity upon all Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners and Captives.</hi>— What all, <hi>ſome will ſay, old Goal birds, Felons,</hi> and <hi>Traitors?</hi> Although the <hi>Prayer</hi> chiefly means <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners</hi> for <hi>Debt,</hi> and <hi>Captives</hi> in <hi>War,</hi> (and ſo we may underſtand the Prayer of <hi>Aſaph, Let the Sighing of the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner come before thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 79.11.</note> 
               <hi>according to the greatneſs of thy Power: Preſerve thou thoſe that are appointed to die.</hi> And that in another <hi>Pſalm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 102.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>He hath looked down from the height of his Sanctuary; from Heaven did the Lord behold the Earth: To hear the Groaning of the Priſoner, to looſe thoſe that are appointed to Death; or the Children of Death.</hi>) Yet it will take in alſo the moſt Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Malefactors,</hi> that need the more Pity, by how much <hi>they</hi> leſs pity them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and we ſhall do well to Pray for the <hi>Thief</hi> on the <hi>Croſs,</hi> the <hi>Murderer</hi> at the <hi>Goal-houſe,</hi> that God would make them <hi>Penitent,</hi> and accept of their <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; break</hi> the <hi>Stony</hi> Heart, and not <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe</hi> the <hi>broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly and Seventhly,—Defend and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the Fatherleſs Children and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows; and all that are Deſolate and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. Provide</hi> for the <hi>Deſolate,</hi> and <hi>defend</hi> the <hi>Oppreſſed.</hi> And ſurely we
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:36099:22"/>ought to Pray for <hi>thoſe</hi> who are God's <hi>Special</hi> Care, ſo <hi>Special,</hi> that he intitles himſelf there-from in the <hi>ſixty eight Pſalm;</hi> where God is repreſented riding in <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant</hi> Majeſty, and <hi>one</hi> would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a <hi>Proclamation</hi> of ſuch <hi>Titles,</hi> as <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> &amp;c. but inſtead thereof we hear, <hi>A Father of the Fatherleſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>and a Judge of the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows is God in his holy Habitation. God ſetteth the Solitary in Families: He bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out thoſe which are bound with Chains.</hi> The <hi>Widow</hi> hath loſt <hi>the Guide of her Youth,</hi> and the <hi>Staff</hi> of her <hi>Age;</hi> and the <hi>Fatherleſs</hi> the beſt <hi>Friend</hi> he can have upon Earth; and therefore we pray that God would be to them <hi>Friend,</hi> and <hi>Father,</hi> and <hi>Husband.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now that we may not leave any ſort of Men out of our Prayers; it follows, <hi>That it would pleaſe thee to have Mercy upon all Men.</hi> All Men? What <hi>Reprobates? Apoſtates?</hi> thoſe that have <hi>ſinned the Sin unto Death?</hi> Who are <hi>Reprobates,</hi> &amp;c. we know not; but we know St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts that <hi>Supplications, Prayers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1</note> 
               <hi>Interceſſions— be made for all Men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.3.</note> Giving this reaſon, <hi>For this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Who will have all Men to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:36099:22"/>be ſaved, and to come unto the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth.</hi> I know how many <hi>Diſtinctions</hi> are made to reſtrain the <hi>All</hi> in theſe <hi>places;</hi> which if they will hold good <hi>there,</hi> they will alſo hold good in this <hi>Prayer;</hi> and then <hi>one</hi> of any <hi>Perſwaſion</hi> may joyn with us in it.</p>
            <p>But there is one fort of Men, for whom the Heart of Man hath little liſt to pray; to wit, <hi>Enemies, Perſecutors, and Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers:</hi> Now to prevent the tacit <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,</hi> our <hi>Church</hi> hath <hi>added</hi> a Prayer for <hi>them,</hi> that God would <hi>forgive</hi> them, <hi>and turn their Hearts.</hi> I ſay <hi>added,</hi> for neither <hi>it</hi> nor any of the forementioned <hi>Charitable Prayers</hi> (except for the <hi>Poor</hi> and <hi>Captives</hi>) are in that <hi>Primer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I given a plain Account of this incomparable <hi>Prayer,</hi> our ſolemn <hi>Litany;</hi> which is not obſcure in it ſelf, but yet hath been much miſunderſtood; and therefore I have laboured to beget a right underſtanding of the ſame. And if what I have ſaid, be not ſufficient to remove the <hi>Prejudices</hi> and <hi>Prepoſſeſſions</hi> of thoſe, who under a Pretence of <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Spirit,</hi> have taught the <hi>People</hi> to deſpiſe both <hi>this,</hi> and all other Set <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Prayer;</hi> yet I hope <hi>at leaſt</hi> it
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:36099:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>may not prove altogether unuſeful to ſuch <hi>Devout</hi> Members of our <hi>Church</hi> (for whoſe ſake it was chiefly intended) that are deſirous both to know <hi>what</hi> it is they pray for in every <hi>part</hi> and <hi>parcel</hi> of <hi>it,</hi> and heartily to pray for the <hi>ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A Brief Expoſition on the Creed, the Lord's Prayer, and Ten Commandments. To which is added the Doctrine of the <hi>Sacraments.</hi> By <hi>Iſaac Barrow,</hi> D. D. And late Maſter of <hi>Trinity</hi> College, <hi>Cambridge.</hi> This on the Creed never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Publiſh'd.</p>
            <p>Advice to young Perſons, relating both to Faith and Practice. Contain'd in ſome plain directions how to Demean themſelves. Together with ſome few motives to the Obſervation of what is here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended. in Octavo. Price 4 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Family Religion: or the Exerciſe of Prayer and Devotion in private Families. By the late Reverend Dr. <hi>Payne,</hi> late Miniſter of <hi>White-Chappel.</hi> In 24es. Price 2 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Method of daily Devotion, A Method of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion for the Lords Day. Likewiſe ſeveral ſmall Books againſt Debauchery, Profaneneſs, Blaſphemy, Curſing and Swearing, &amp;c. All by Dr. <hi>Aſcheton.</hi> In 24es. Price 2 <hi>d</hi> Each, and ſomething Cheaper to them that give away Numbers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:36099:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
